{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One man in this family was exiled to Venice after his city’s failure to conquer Lucca and later exiled the Albizzi and Strozzi families on his return. Archbishop Francesco Salviati was executed for his role in one plot against a member of this family, which resulted in the death of Giulano, the Pazzi Conspiracy. That member of this family patronized Botticelli and was known as the Magnificent. Cosimo and Lorenzo were from, for ten points, what Florentine banking family?",
      "answer": "de Medici"
    },
    {
      "question": "This location may have been inadvertently burned by a shepherd who was chasing after his sheep by torchlight. 100 rivers of flowing mercury were recreated in this location according to Sima Qian. This location was modeled upon the capital of Xianyang and housed inside a pyramid-shaped mound in Lintong Province. Thousands of uniquely sculpted soldiers were placed in this location to aid the emperor in the afterlife. For ten points, identify this tomb complex near Xian where the Terracotta Army was placed.",
      "answer": [
        "mausoleum of Qin Shihuangdi",
        "necropolis of Qin Shihuangdi",
        "tomb before mention"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Because Arthur Chilson and two associates sailed to Africa in 1902 to establish this religion, Kenya today has the most members of this religion. The acronym “SPICES” is used to remember principles in this religion. Members of this religion attend business gatherings called Yearly Meetings. Members of this religion believe in God as one’s “inner light.” For ten points, name this religion, founded by George Fox and practiced by Richard Nixon, Mary Dyer, and William Penn.",
      "answer": [
        "Religious Society of Friends",
        "Quakers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man’s governorship, James Rector was killed during “Bloody Thursday” at People’s Park. Though supposedly pro-life, this man signed a “Therapeutic Abortion Act” resulting in over 2 million abortions in his state. The Black Panthers protested this man’s signing of the Mulford Act, and he was succeeded by Jerry Brown’s first term. For 10 points, name this Republican governor of California and former actor who later defeated Jimmy Carter for President in 1980.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This non-Asian country’s “Emergency” in the 1950s led to the signing of the London-Zu¨rich Agreements. This country was the subject of the failed 2004 Annan Plan. This country was invaded in Operation Attila after a successful coup led by EOKA-B. This country is divided by the Green Line and split over the cause of enosis, or unification with Greece. For 10 points, name this 3rd-largest Mediterranean island split between a Turkish northern half and a Greek southern half.",
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "question": "After beating Red Star Belgrade in the 1958 European Cup quarterfinals, this team suffered 11 casualties in a plane crash in Munich; survivors included Ray Wood, Bobby Charlton, and manager Matt Busby. A memorial to the Munich disaster is on display at this team’s home stadium, Old Trafford, where one of its stands is named for legendary manager Sir Alex Ferguson. For ten points, name this English football club whose 13 titles are the most in Premier League history.",
      "answer": "Manchester United Football Club"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was investigated by Thomas Walsh after John McKendrick was tipped-off. A court case stemming from this event granted Congress the power to compel testimony. McGrain v. Daugherty grew out of this event during which Albert Fall became the first Cabinet member to be sent to jail. The leasing of Elk Hills in exchange for bribes was central to, for ten points, what oil scandal that rocked Warren G. Harding’s presidency?",
      "answer": "Teapot Dome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Troops on this campaign stopped to aid Alfonso I in the capture of Moorish Lisbon, their only success in this campaign. This campaign culminated in a slaughter at a vineyard outside Damascus. Manuel Komnenos was accused of colluding with the Seljuk Turks against this campaign’s leaders, Louis VII and Conrad III. After the County of Edessa fell to Zengi, Bernard of Clairvaux recruited soldiers for this campaign. For ten points, name this 1147 campaign called by Pope Eugene III.",
      "answer": "Second Crusade"
    },
    {
      "question": "Racial covenants on housing were found unconstitutional in a case originating in this city, Shelley v. Kraemer. The Eads Bridge in this city was the first bridge across the Mississippi south of the Missouri. This former location of the Pruitt-Igoe public housing projects is home to a weighted catenary designed by Eero Saarinen symbolizing its connection to the American West. For 10 points, name this Midwestern city home to the Gateway Arch.",
      "answer": "St. Louis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s aide, John Armstrong, was caught attempting to lead a military coup in the Newburgh Conspiracy. The Baron de Kalb died while under the command of this man as part of the disastrous Battle of Camden. The Conway Cabal aimed to replace George Washington with this man. This man claimed credit for defending the Bemis Heights from John Burgoyne which led to resentment from Benedict Arnold. For ten points, name this man who commanded American forces at Saratoga.",
      "answer": "Horatio Gates"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "UlricNeisserstudiedthememoryofaparticipantinthisevent,confidentlydeclaringthatthatperson’s memory was not equal to a tape recorder. J. Fred Buzhardt was brought over from the Department of Defense during this event in order to investigate John Dean. During a Sam Ervin-led committee on this scandal, Howard Baker asked, “What did the President know and when did he know it?” A break-in at the headquarters of the Democratic National Committee sparked, for ten points, what scandal that ended Richard Nixon’s presidency?",
        "answer": "Watergate scandal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the midst of the Watergate Scandal, a different scandal involving tax evasion caused the resignation of this Vice President.",
        "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two molecules of this compound and two chlorine atoms bind a central platinum atom in the chemotherapy drug cisplatin. Friedrich Raschig used an excess of this gas in a process for producing hydrazine. Carl Bosch was employed to further develop a technique to produce it from its constituent gases; that technique was developed by Fritz Haber and drastically increased global food production. For ten points, name this gas important in fertilizer and cleaning solution, with the chemical formula NH . 3",
        "answer": [
          "ammonia",
          "NH before mentioned 3"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1828, Friedrich Wohler [voh-ler] synthesized this eight-atom compound by treating silver cyanate with ammonium chloride, the first time an organic compound had been synthesized artificially from inorganic compounds.",
        "answer": "urea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Samogitian tribe was converted to Christianity while living around this body of water. The Torstensson War was fought over levies on ships entering this body of water, the Sound Dues. Konrad von Jungingen drove one organization out of Visby on an island in this body of water. Defeat to Sweden in the Ingrian War resulted in Russia losing direct access to this body of water. For ten points, name this sea, whose trade was once dominated by the Hanseatic League during the late middle ages.",
        "answer": "Baltic Sea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Victual Brothers established their headquarters at Visby initially to counter this German port city. Along with Danzig, this free city contributed the greatest share of Hanseatic trade in the Baltic.",
        "answer": "Lu¨beck"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s Forward Party became the largest party in parliament in its first election in 2006. The Alignment Party is the only party ever to have formed a majority government in this country. This country’s Labour Party dominated politics up until 1977 and is currently led by Avi Gabbay. In this country’s 2019 elections, the Blue and White party led by Benny Gantz won 35 seats in the Knesset. For ten points, name this country currently led by the leader of the Likud Party, Benjamin Netanyahu.",
        "answer": "Israel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This wife of Benjamin Netanyahu was indicted in a corruption case after being accused of ordering meals at the state’s expense.",
        "answer": "Sara Netanyahu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man demanded “Let that spot be purified, or let it cease to be of New England” in a speech denouncing slavery given at Plymouth Rock. This man pleaded “Let us make our generation one of the strongest and brightest links in the golden chain” in his Seventh of March Speech. In one court case, this man argued “It is, Sir, as I have said, a small college. And yet there are those who love it!.” For ten points, name this longtime Senator and orator who declared “liberty and union, now and forever, one and inseparable” in his “Second Reply to Hayne.”",
        "answer": "Daniel Webster"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Webster defended this “small college”, his alma mater, in a case that pitted its private charter against the Governor of New Hampshire.",
        "answer": "Dartmouth College"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader with this name was strongly influenced by the Duke of Lerma. Another leader with this name married Elizabeth Farnese and was the first Bourbon leader of his country. The most famous leader with this name signed the Treaty of Joinville and annexed Portugal. That leader with this name was the son of Charles V and sent a large military force to defeat Elizabeth I. For ten points, give this name of five Spanish kings, including the monarch who dispatched the Spanish Armada.",
        "answer": [
          "Philip",
          "Philip III,",
          "Philip V,",
          "Philip II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Philip II was briefly married to this Queen of England who burned many Protestants at the stake and was succeeded by Elizabeth I.",
        "answer": [
          "Mary I",
          "Bloody Mary"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A choral symphony by this composer includes a depiction of the life of Anne Frank, and this composer’s third symphony celebrates May Day. This composer was attacked by his government in the anonymous article “Muddle Instead of Music.” This composer of 15 symphonies, such as those named for the years 1905 and 1917, included a snare-drum ostinato backed “Invasion” theme in his seventh. For ten points, name this Soviet composer of the “Leningrad” Symphony.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the pieces that Shostakovich used to redeem himself after the attack by the Pravda article was this one, a D-minor symphony that ends in a triumphant D-major brass fanfare.",
        "answer": [
          "Symphony 5",
          "fifth symphony,",
          "opus 47"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 7 March speech preceded a conflict in this modern-day country. This country was the site of the largest surrender of troops since World War II, which occurred during a conflict that began with the genocidal Operation Searchlight. This country’s first female prime minister was the BNP leader Khaleda Zia, and it is currently led by the Awami League. This country gained its independence after the surrender of Yahya Khan’s forces in 1971. For ten points, name this South Asian country once known as East Pakistan.",
        "answer": "Bangladesh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bangladeshi independence was declared by Sheikh Mujibur Rahman in this Bangladeshi ancient port city, the country’s second largest after Dhaka.",
        "answer": "Chittagong or Chattogram"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "3. Revolutions",
      "prompt": "Name the person who died since last year’s High School NHBB Nationals who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Served as a Senator from Arizona and lost the presidency to Obama in 2008.",
          "answer": "John McCain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Told voters to “read [his] lips...no new taxes” before losing to Bill Clinton in 1992.",
          "answer": [
            "George Herbert Walker Bush",
            "Bush the Elder, Bush the 41st"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-created numerous Marvel Universe characters, like Spider-Man and Black Panther.",
          "answer": "Stan Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as a UN Secretary General from Ghana.",
          "answer": "Kofi Annan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-founded Microsoft and owned the Seattle Seahawks.",
          "answer": "Paul Allen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served two terms as president of Peru before killing himself this month.",
          "answer": "Alan Garcia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created an iconic sculpture spelling the word LOVE and changed his last name to his birth state.",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Indiana",
            "Robert Clark"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed in prison at age 89 in October after leading the Winter Hill Gang near Boston.",
          "answer": "Whitey Bulger"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "May 1968 in France",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Number of the Republic in which it started, founded in 1958.",
          "answer": "5th Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "French President and leader in World War II who fled the country on May 29.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Feminist author of The Second Sex, who supported the protest movement.",
          "answer": "Simone de Beauvoir"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paris university, founded in 1253, that was attended by many student protesters.",
          "answer": "La Sorbonne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislative body that was dissolved on May 30.",
          "answer": "National Assembly or L’assembl´ee nationale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presidential successor of Mitterrand; he helped to negotiate an end to the student riots.",
          "answer": "Jacques Chirac"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister and namesake of a Parisian cultural center who helped diffuse the protests.",
          "answer": "Georges Pompidou"
        },
        {
          "question": "Student protest leader, known as “Dany le Rouge,” who later became a leader of the Green Party in the EU Parliament.",
          "answer": "Daniel Cohn-Bendit"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Revolutions",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city where the Hungarian Revolution was crushed by Soviet tanks.",
          "answer": "Budapest"
        },
        {
          "question": "Implement used to kill Louis XVI [16] during the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "guillotine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-political revolution characterized by increased use of steam power and mechanization.",
          "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Color of the 20th century revolution in agricultural production, led by Norman Borlaug’s work.",
          "answer": "Green Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year known for the “Spring of Nations” in Europe.",
          "answer": "1848"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator overthrown by Fidel Castro in the Cuban Revolution.",
          "answer": "Fulgencio Batista"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flower that names the revolution in which Antonio Salazar was overthrown.",
          "answer": "Carnation Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number given to the Burmese uprising in which General Ne Win resigned.",
          "answer": [
            "8888 Uprising , but",
            "it however it’s said"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the rule of this man, an anarchist rally was crushed in the Red Flag Incident which led to an assassination plot called the High Treason Incident two years later. In one document, this ruler promised to break off the (20 pts)",
        "“evil customs of the past” and base everything on the “just laws of Nature.” In 1895, this ruler’s government began several policies under the slogan “Enrich the country, (10 pts)",
        "strengthen the military.” This ruler dismantled his country’s domain system replacing it with a system of 72 prefectures. For ten points, name this Emperor of Japan who immediately began westernizing the country after seizing power in 1871."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Meiji",
        "Mutsuhito"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A commission led by Elie Wiesel investigated this country’s conduct during World War Two, including its suppression of the Legionnaires’ Rebellion. This country switched allegiances in WWII after a coup led by King (20 pts)",
        "Michael. The “Everything for [this] Country” Party grew out of a group whose members were called “greenshirts,” the (10 pts)",
        "Iron Guard. One leader of this country organized the Securitate secret police but was executed during this country’s 1989 Revolution. For ten points, name this Eastern Bloc country once led by Nicolae Ceaucescu out of Bucharest."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Romania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These locations were the focus of a John Collier-sponsored “New Deal” which aimed to create, among other things, economic self-sufficiency. Starting in the 1940s, these locations were the target of a (20 pts)",
        "“termination” policy that unexempted them from federal and state taxes. A rock band named Coyote Springs is the subject of a Sherman Alexie novel named for the (10 pts)",
        "“blues” of these locations. The case California v. Cabazon ruled that these places can have gambling facilities as long as that type of gambling is legal within the state they are located. The Trail of Tears resulted in an increased number of, for ten points, what areas of land managed by Native American tribes?"
      ],
      "answer": "Indian reservations"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One unnamed character in this work is given the name Musa in a response to this work that is told from the perspective of Musa’s brother Harun and was written by Kamel (20 pts)",
        "Daoud. The main character of this novel defends Raymond Sint´es’ beating his girlfriend and angrily rejects God while in prison. That main character is sentenced to be executed after the fact that he (10 pts)",
        "failed to cry at his mother’s funeral was used to show he felt no remorse for shooting an Arab on the beach. The Mersault Investigation was written in response to, for ten points, what existential novel by Albert Camus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Stranger",
        "L’´etranger"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) By annexing the Decapole, Metz, and Verdun, this treaty gave France a foothold in Alsace-Lorraine. After this treaty was signed, Bremen claimed imperial immediacy to avoid being annexed by (20 pts)",
        "Sweden, which also received Western Pomerania. Balance of power and non-interference in other states’ affairs form part of the concept of (10 pts)",
        "sovereignty named after this treaty, which formally recognized the independence of Switzerland and the Netherlands. The Peace of Augsburg was reaffirmed in, for ten points, what treaty signed in Mu¨nster and Osnabruck which ended the Thirty Years’ War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist insisted that two of his works, including Dido Building Carthage were displayed next to two works by Claude Lorrain. Pink and red swirls in the bottom left of one unfinished canvas title this artist’s (20 pts)",
        "Sunrise with Sea Monsters. Black storm clouds and an avalanche menace an army in one work by this artist, who symbolized the end of a naval era in one work that depicts a (10 pts)",
        "steam-powered tug under a setting sun pulling a veteran ship of the line of the Battle of Trafalgar. For ten points, name this artist of Hannibal Crossing the Alps and The Fighting Temeraire."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Mallard William Turner"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While working as a consultant for Abe Ribicoff, this man was targeted by private investigators sent by James Roche. This man founded the Critical Mass Energy Project as part of his (20 pts)",
        "anti-nuclear efforts in the mid-1970s. This author of Crashing the Party led a group of namesake “Raiders” that investigated the FTC. A chapter titled (10 pts)",
        "“The Sporty Corvair” opened this man’s critical book on car manufacturing safety standards, Unsafe at Any Speed. For ten points, name this public advocate and spoiler candidate for the Green Party in the 2000 U.S. presidential election."
      ],
      "answer": "Ralph Nader"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker described the prioritization of scientific rationalization in secularizing Western society as its “disenchantment” in his work (20 pts)",
        "The Sociology of Religion. This thinker defined a state as the entity that monopolizes the legitimate use of violence in a series of 1919 Munich lectures, Politics as a Vocation. This thinker’s most famous work argues that (10 pts)",
        "Calvinist anxiety over predestination led to an economic system whose late industrial variety he described as an “iron cage.” For ten points, name this sociologist who wrote The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism."
      ],
      "answer": "Max Weber"
    }
  ]
}